Guide to the John Benjamin Harris Papers, 1955-1991 and undated RL.00513
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Benjamin Harris papers
1955-1991 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Harris, John Benjamin, 1927-
RL.00513
2.1 Linear Feet
John Benjamin Harris is Professor Emeritus of Management and Marketing at Virginia State University. He pioneered governmental and commercial awareness of African American advertising markets and, in the 1970s, became the Director of the Virginia State Office of Minority Business Enterprise and Special Assistant to the Governor for Minority Enterprise. The John Benjamin Harris Papers span the years 1955-1991 and include scholarly articles, corporate reports and proposals, product labels, 16mm film reels, and audio tapes. Materials represent Harris' academic and professional work at New York University and Virginia State University as well as his work for the Virginia State Office of Minority Business Enterprise. Topics touched on in the collection include minority business enterprises; minority markets and minorities (especially African Americans) as consumers; and African American mass media. In addition, the collection reflects Harris' work for the advertising industry with employers including Cunningham & Walsh, Inc., the Leo Burnett Company, Inc., and the Ted Bates Company. Brands represented include Alka-Seltzer (Miles Laboratories), Campbell Soup, Coca-Cola, Cleveland Electric, Eastman Kodak, Pillsbury, and Schlitz.
790 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Use copies are available in the collections.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Benjamin Harris Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2005.
Biographical Note
Biographical timeline
1927 Jan. 15 Born, Chesterfield County, VA
1933-1940 Kingsland Elementary School, Chesterfield County, VA
1943 Certificate of Barber Practice and Science from Virginia State College Trade School
1944 American Campaign Medal Graduated, D. Webster Davis High School (Virginia State College Laboratory School)
1944-1945 U.S. Army Air Force Virginia State College, Petersburg, VA
1947-1949 Virginia State College, Department of Military Science
1949 Commissioned U.S. Quartermaster (QM)
1950 Sept. 2 Married Ruth Hortense Coles
1950-1953 1st Lieutenant, U.S. Army Corps
1951 B.S. in Business Administration, Virginia State University
1952 Instructor in Military Tactics and Strategy, U.S Army QM School
1954 Jan. 2 Assistant Hotel Manager, Love B. Woods, Inc., New York, NY Son, John Jr., born
1954-1966 Captain, U.S. Army Officers Reserves
1955 M.B.A. in Marketing and Management, New York University, Graduate School of Business Administration Special Advertising Representative and Space Salesman, AFRO-AMERICAN Newspapers, Inc., Baltimrore, MD
1955-1967 Assistant Professor of Business and Economics and Director of Publicity, Virginia Union University
1957 Dec. 25 Daughter, Vita Michelle, born
1964 Fellow, General Electric and National Association of Manufacturers, Claremont Men's Graduate School, Advanced Certificate in Basic Economics
1965 General Electric Fellow,University of Chicago, Graduate School of Business, Certificate in Applied Economics Special Projects Officer, International Business Machines, Office Products Division
1965-1971 National Urban League Fellow
1966 Certificate in Macro Economic Theory, Case Institute of Technology. Republic Steel Fellow/Economics-in-Action Fellow
1967 Retired from Army Reserves Advertising Planner and Special Markets Assistant, Eastman Kodak Company
1968 Associate Professor of Marketing and Management, School of Business, Virginia State University General and Special Markets Advisor to Vice President, Pillsbury Company, Grocery Products Division Consultant on Minority Affairs, U.S. Navy Department NDE Fellow, Audio Visual Media Technology, Graduate School of Education, Virginia State College (now Virginia State University)
1969 Certificate in Advanced Advertising Management, Montauk, NY Association of National Advertisers (ANA) Assistant Account Executive, Benton & Bowles Advertising Agency
1970 Member, President's Inter-Agency Socio-Economic Policy Staff for Minority Business Enterprise
1971 Assistant Brand Manager, The Proctor and Gamble Company, Toilet Goods Division
1972 Associate Professor of Marketing, School of Business, Virginia State University Evening School (10 years) Director, Virginia State Office of Minority Business Enterprise and Special Assistant to Governor for Minority Enterprise, Office of the Governor, Commonwealth of Virginia Consultant and Interim Director, Church Hill Economic Development Corporation Information Specialist, USDA, Agriculture Stabilization and Conservation Service (ASCS) Certificate of Honor presented by Virginia Union University president Allix B. James "In recognition of distinguished services to the University 1955-1972"
1973 Member, Southern Growth Policies Board (6 years) Honorary Citizen of Dallas, TX
1974 African American Institute and Howard University Fellow to West Africa Graduate School of Education, Howard University. Concentration in African American Relations, emphasis on marketing, business, and economic development
Circa 1974 Certificate in Marketing Education, U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare
1978 Stanford University, concentrated course on the "Role of Business in Society," ROBIS Institute/Intercollegiate Studies Institute, Certificate
1979 Director, Virginia State office of Minority Business Enterprise and Special Assistant to Governor for Minority Enterprise, Office of the Governor, Commonwealth of Virginia
1983 Fellow, The Direct Marketing Educational Foundation, Inc. and Direct Marketing Day Fellow, Cleveland Scholarship Program, Inc. and Professorial Intern in Marketing, Cleveland Illuminating Company
2014 June 11 Died, Richmond, Va.
Collection Overview
The John Benjamin Harris Papers span the years 1955-1991 and include scholarly articles, corporate reports and proposals, product labels, 16mm film reels, and audio tapes. Materials represent Harris' academic and professional work at New York University and Virginia State University as well as his work for the Virginia State Office of Minority Business Enterprise. Topics touched on in the collection include minority business enterprises; minority markets and minorities (especially African Americans) as consumers; and African American mass media. In addition, the collection reflects Harris' work for the advertising industry with employers including Cunningham & Walsh, Inc., the Leo Burnett Company, Inc., and the Ted Bates Company. Brands represented include Alka-Seltzer (Miles Laboratories), Campbell Soup, Coca-cola, Cleveland Electric, Eastman Kodak, Pillsbury, and Schlitz.
The collection is organized into three series: Writings, Package Labels, and Audiovisual Materials. The Writings Series includes scholarly articles, reports, and proposals from Harris' academic and professional career in marketing research. The Package Labels series includes images of Campbell Soup Company branded product labels. The Audiovisual Materials series includes reels of television and radio advertisements for various company brands and advertising agencies.
Related Material
Other materials relating to this collection may be found in the following Hartman Center collections within the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives: the Domestic Advertisements Collection; the Granger Tripp Papers; the Shirley F. Woodell Papers; the Marketing Vertical File; and the Edward G. Wilson Papers. Also, related materials may be found in the Bates Worldwide, Inc. Records, the John E. Brennan Outdoor Advertising Survey Reports; the D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles Archives; the Wayne P. Ellis Collection of Kodakiana; the Kensinger Jones Papers; and the Gene Frederico Papers.
Minority business enterprises -- Government policy -- United States; Marketing research -- United States; Marketing research; African Americans -- Case studies; Labels (identifying artifacts); Brand name products -- United States; African Americans and mass media; African Americans and mass media -- United States; Advertising -- Research; Advertising -- Research -- United States; Advertising executives; Advertising executives -- United States; Minority business enterprises -- Virginia; Advertising -- Brand name products; Radio advertising; Minority consumers -- United States; Audiotapes; Television advertising; Motion pictures (visual works); 16mm; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Harris, John Benjamin, 1927-; Eastman Kodak Company; New York University -- Faculty; Miles Laboratories; Leo Burnett Company; Jos. Schlitz Brewing Co.; Cunningham & Walsh, Inc. [Not LC]; Coca-Cola Company; Cleveland Electric Illuminating Company; Campbell Soup Company; Pillsbury Company; Ted Bates Advertising; Virginia State University -- Faculty
- Writings Series, 1955-1991 and undated, 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains manuscripts of academic papers, business proposals, and reports written by Harris. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - American Negro and His Media, The Leo Burnett Company, Inc., 1966 (Box 1)
  - Analysis of Consumer Advertising to the Washington, D.C. Negro Market, MBA Thesis, New York University, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Analysis of Virginia's Minority Bank Deposit Program, Virginia State Office of Minority Business Enterprise, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Case for Negro-Oriented Newspapers, Eastman Kodak Company, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Communications and the Negro Market: Framework and Strategy, The Pillsbury Company, 1968 (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - CMD Products (Still & Movie Equipment and Film) 1967-68 Marketing Plans Proposal, Eastman Kodak Company, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Effective Advertising to the Negro Market: Some Basic Guidelines, Eastman Kodak Company, 1967 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Export Strategies for the 1990s: A Strategic Plan for Minority Firms' Participation in Global Markets, 1991 (Box 1)
    [A research proposal with 2 enclosures--Appendix A: Personal Data--Export Potential for Minority Enterprises in the Caribbean and West African Countries; and Appendix B: Sample Publications]
  - Minority Market Relations Abstract, The Cleveland Electric Illuminating Company, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Minority Market Relations, The Cleveland Electric Illuminating Company, 1983 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Negro Market in America Today, Bob Dore Associates, undated (Box 2)
- Package Labels, undated, 1 box
  Contains photocopies of Campbell Soup Company products, arranged alphabetically by brand.
  - Bounty (Box 2)
    [Bounty from Campbell's Corned Beef Hash, Bounty from Campbell's Chili con Carne (with Beans), Bounty from Campbell's Beef Stew, Bounty from Campbell's Chicken Stew, Bounty from Campbell's Chili-Mac: Macaroni, Beef and Beans in a Zesty Sauce]
  - Campbell's (Box 2)
    [Campbell's Pork & Beans with Tomato Sauce; Campbell's Beans & Ground Beef in Barbecue Sauce, Campbell's Beans & Franks in Tomato Sauce, Campbell's Barbecue Beans: 4 Kinds of Beans in Mild Barbecue Sauce, Campbell's Old Fashioned Beans in Molasses Sauce, Campbell's Homestyle Tomato Juice, V-8 Cocktail Vegetable Juice, Campbell's Condensed Bean with Bacon Soup, Campbell's Condensed Tomato Soup, Campbell's Condensed Chicken Vegetable Soup, Campbell's Condensed Chicken Noodle Soup]
  - Franco-American (Box 2)
    [Franco-American Macaroni 'n Beef in Tomato Sauce: Elbow Macaroni with Ground Beef, Franco-American Spaghetti-Os in Tomato and Cheese Sauce, Franco-American Spaghetti-Os with Sliced Franks in Tomato Sauce, Franco-American Spaghetti in Tomato Sauce with Cheese, Franco-American Spaghetti with Ground Beef in Tomato Sauce, Franco-American Spaghetti with Meatballs in Tomato Sauce, Franco-American Italian Style Spaghetti in Tomato-Cheese Sauce, Franco-American Mushroom Gravy, Franco-American Spaghetti Sauce with Meat, Franco-American Spaghetti Sauce with Mushrooms, Franco-American Chicken Gravy, Franco-American Beef Gravy, Franco-American Giblet Gravy]
  - Swanson HP (Box 2)
    [Swanson Boned Turkey with Broth, Swanson Chicken Spread, Swanson Boned Chicken with Broth, Swanson Chicken a la King, Swanson Chicken in golden gravy (Chicken fricasee), Swanson Clear Chicken Broth, Swanson Chunks o' Chicken]
- Audiovisual Materials 1969-1982 and undated, 3 boxes
  Contains sound tapes and film reels of TV and radio advertisements for Jack Tinker and Partners Advertising Agency (Alka Seltzer), Jos. Schlitz Brewing Co. (Old Milwaukee Beer), The Coca-Cola Company, The Ted Bates Company, Cunningham & Walsh, Inc. (Old Milwaukee).
  - Originals
    Conditions Governing Access
    Originals audiovisual items are closed to researchers. Use Copies are available in the collection.
    - Audiotape
      - AV1. Jos. Schlitz Brewing Co. Old Milwaukee Beer C&W 911. Undated. Format: .25" (7.5 ips.). Use Copy UC-1 in collection. (Box 3)
        [Contains radio commercials produced by Cunningham & Walsh and recorded by Gotham Recording Corporation: 1. R-OM-60-69-118 Louie; 2. R-OM-60-69-119 Beer Truck; 3. R-OM-60-69-93 Anncr. - Music; 4. R-OM-60-69-131 Delivery Man; 5. R-OM-60-69-122 Dentist; 6. R-OM-60-69-126 Documentary; 7. R-OM-60-69-1128 Race Track; 8. R-OM-30-69-120 Repeat; 9. R-OM-30-69-121 Inflation; 10. R-OM-30-69-129 Skeptic; 11. R-OM-20-69-71 Match; 12. R-OM-20-69-77R Echo;13. R-OM-10-69-76R Echo; 14. R-OM-10-69-74 Why]
      - AV2. Things go better with Coke. 1969. Format: .25" (7.5 ips.) TRT: 37.5 minutes. Use Copy UC-1 in collection. (Box 3)
        [Contains radio commercials produced by McCann-Erikson, Inc. and The Coca-Cola Company: spots numbered 1-4 Brooklyn Bridge :60; :60; :30; :30; spots numbered 5-8 B.J. Thomas :60; :60; :30; :30; spots numbered 9-10 Carla Thomas :60; :30; spots numbered 11-12 Jerry Butler :60; :30; spots numbered 13-14 Carla Thomas/Jerry Butler :60; :30; spots numbered 15-18 Vanilla Fudge :60; :60; :30; :30; spots numbered 19-22 Moody Blues :60; :60; :30; :30; spots numbered 23-25 Ray Charles/Aretha Franklin I, spots numbered 26-28 Ray Charles/Aretha Franklin II :90; :60; :30; spots numbered 29-31 Ray Charles :90; :60; :30; spots numbered 32-34 Aretha Franklin :90; :60; :30; spots numbered 35-38 Tommy Boyce/Bobby Hart :60; :60; :30; :30; spots numbered 39-42 The 5th Dimension :60; :60; :30; :30; spots numbered 43-46 Gladys Night and the Pips :60; :60; :30; :30]
    - Film
      - AV3. Alka Seltzer. Undated. Format: 16mm. Use Copy UC-2 in collection. (Box 3)
        [Contains television commercials produced by Jack Tinker & Partners and entitled: Caveman AS-60-215; Heartburn Man AS-60-179; Trailmaster TV-69-3-30; Bundle of Nerves N-30-28; Slow Pan S-60-8; Jim/Jamie 69-0472-30; Totem Pole 69-0791-60; Moon Trip 69-0500-60. Also includes commercials for other Miles Laboratory products: Nervine, Sungard, Bactine, One-A-Day, and Chocks]
      - AV4. Coca-Cola Reel. Undated. Format: 16mm. TRT: 6:08 minutes. Use Copy UC-2 in collection. (Box 3)
        [Contains television commercials produced for The Coca Cola Company: TV6-828c Ray Charles :60; TV6-841c Summer Dimensions :60; TV5-842c Summer Dimensions :50; TV3-843c Summer Dimensions :30; TV8-820c Summer Dimensions :08; TV2-840c Scrambling :20; TV6-816c Summer Goes Better :60; TV5-817c Summer Goes Better :50; TV2-844c Tub :20; TV2-845c Man Drinking :20; TV8-846c Shape :08; TV8-847c Lunch :08]
      - AV5. CHF2 62-75 (2). 1977-1978. Format: 16mm. Use Copy UC-2 in collection. (Box 3)
        [Contains television commercials for Sears Automotive products (Diehard batteries, tires, mufflers, car radios, Sears Car Care Centers)]
      - AV6. Old Milwaukee. Undated. Format: 16mm. TRT: 1 minute. Use Copy UC-2 in collection. (Box 4)
        [Contains televison commercial produced by Cunningham & Walsh, Inc.: OM 60 68 47C 6RTB0. Irish CLR 60 SEC 7296]
      - AV7. Old Milwaukee. Undated. Format: 16mm. TRT: 1 minute. Use Copy UC-2 in collection. (Box 4)
        [Contains television commercials produced by Cunningham & Walsh, Inc.: OM 60 68 50C 6RTB0. Trial CLR 60 sec 7287A]
      - AV8. Old Milwaukee. Undated. Format: 16mm. TRT: 1 minute. Use Copy UC-2 in collection. (Box 4)
        [Contains television commercials produced by Cunningham & Walsh, Inc.: OM 60 68 48C 6RTB0. Where Are You From CLR 60 sec 7296]
      - AV9. CW Old Milwaukee. Undated. Format: 16mm. TRT: 1 minute. Use Copy UC-3 in collection. (Box 4)
        [Contains television commercials produced by Cunningham & Walsh, Inc.: OM 60 68 32C Contract. Showdown CLR 60 sec]
      - AV10. Ted Bates AAF Hall of Fame Induction 3/31/82. 1982. Format: 16mm. TRT: ~10 minutes. Use Copy UC-3 in collection. (Box 4)
      - AV11. Untitled. Undated. 16mm. Use Copy UC-3 in collection. (Box 4)
        [Includes televison commercials for: Zest Beauty Bar (including one commercial in Spanish); Charmin bathroom tissue (Mr. Whipple); Ivory Snow detergent; Scottie tissues; White Cloud bathroom tissue]
      - AV12. Untitled. Undated. 16mm. Use Copy UC-3 in collection. (Box 4)
        [Includes television commercials for: Lilt home permanent; Zest Beauty Bar (including one advertisement featuring an African American actress); TWA; Vick's Formula 44; Prell shampoo; Pepto-Bismol; E.F. Hutton; Chemical Bank New York; Cool Whip; Nyquil cough suppressant; Texaco; Scope mouthwash]
  - Production Masters
    Production masters of audiovisual items are closed to researchers. Use Copies are available in the collection.
    - AVM1. Master for AV1-AV2. Format: DVD. Created: 2008. (Box 5)
    - AVM2-AVM3. Masters for AV3-AV12. Format: Betacam SP. Created: 2008. (Box 5)
  - Use Copies
    - UC1-UC3. Use copies for AV1-AV12. Format: DVD. Created: 2008. (Box 2)